<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>VVater upon the flame: by XX. queries propounded in the spirit of love and meeknesse, to the serious consideration of all Gods people; principally to the fifth monarch men, commonly so called. / By one that loveth the truth, and all good men; and one that neither hath, nor ever had, nor never intendeth to have the least place of profit, or worldly advantage by any change of government whatsoever.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1042</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E989_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204047</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863763</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863763</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115977</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96069)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115977)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 147:E989[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>VVater upon the flame: by XX. queries propounded in the spirit of love and meeknesse, to the serious consideration of all Gods people; principally to the fifth monarch men, commonly so called. / By one that loveth the truth, and all good men; and one that neither hath, nor ever had, nor never intendeth to have the least place of profit, or worldly advantage by any change of government whatsoever.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fifth Monarchy Men --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religion and politics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115977:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>VVATER UPON THE FLAME: BY XX. QUERIES Propounded in the Spirit of LOVE and MEEK<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESSE, To the Serious Conſideration of all GODS PEOPLE; Principally to the <hi>FIFTH MONARCH MEN,</hi> commonly ſo called.</p>
            <p>By One that loveth the Truth, and all Good Men; And One that neither hath, nor ever had, nor never intendeth to have the leaſt <hi>Place</hi> of <hi>Profit,</hi> or Worldly <hi>Advantage</hi> by any <hi>Change</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115977:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115977:2"/>
            <head>Water upon the Flame, OR, QUERIES Propounded in the Spirit of Love and Meekneſſe to the ſerious Conſideration of all Gods People, principally to the FIFTH MONARCH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MEN, commonly ſo called.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether you are not ſubject to the like Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with other men, and conſequently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Errours and Miſtakes as other men? 'Tis certain they that know moſt, <hi>know but in part,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.9. And whether the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence you have had of your pronneſſe to erre, and be confident without cauſe, in ſome things as well as others, do not rationally call for theſe two things? Firſt, To hold your preſent differing thoughts, humbly remembring, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.2. He that <hi>thinketh he knoweth any thing, knoweth nothing as he ought to know.</hi> Secondly, To be alwaies ready to look on other mens things as well as your own, remembring 2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. <hi>Look not every man on his own things, but every man alſo on the things of others.</hi> And 3. Prov. 6. <hi>Lean not to thine own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi> And 12. Rom. 3. <hi>Let every man think ſoberly of himſelf.</hi> Remembring, 12. Rom. 16. <hi>Be not wiſe in your own conceit.</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, 1. Pet. 5.5. <hi>Yea all of you be ſubject one to another, and be clothed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115977:3"/>with humility,</hi> and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.32. <hi>The Spirits of the Prophets are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Prophets.</hi> Wherefore, You that are but few in compariſon of all the Godly, to adapt a particular Opinion, differing from the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of al Chriſtians that either do now, or ever did live in the world: and to hold it with a high and impoſing Spirit, can poſſibly conſiſt with obedience to thoſe Scripture Exhortations, or a due ſence of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent darkneſs, blindneſs, and ignorance, that poor mortalls groan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether the ſaying of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> be not rational and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy your conſideration: <hi>A few dark and obſcure places of Scripture ought to receive expoſition agreeable to the current of Scriptures?</hi> Now whether the Scriptures of the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Revelations,</hi> whereupon you ground your differing Opinion and high Purpoſes, be not dark Scriptures in compariſon of other Scriptures of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; I leave to your conſideration.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether any interpretation of <hi>Daniels</hi> Propheſie, or any other which contradicteth the plain &amp; expreſs Doctrine and Practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, ought to be admitted for Truth, or the Ground of any Practice,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn</hi> 3.31. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn</hi> 5.37. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.23. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.2.</note> much leſs the Ground of War and Blood. The Quereſt conceiveth No. For that, Firſt, <hi>Chriſt came from above and is above all,</hi> the annointed Prophet of the whole world, whom the Father himſelf hath born Witneſs to, by an audible Voyce, and Summoned the whole world to hear him upon pain of death, and becauſe the Apoſtles of Chriſt received ſpecial Orders from Chriſt, for the good Government of the New Teſtament Churches, until he come again, and thoſe in very plain and eaſie tearms. And Thirdly, becauſe to accept of any interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their Doctrine, which contradicteth his own Doctrine, and perſonal Practice, would ſet Chriſt againſt himſelf, the ill conſequence whereof, is not perhaps preſently, or eaſily apprehended 'Tis certain the Prophets ſpake by the ſame Spirit; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11. therefore nothing contradictory to him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether that Expoſition of the Prophets, and <hi>Revelation</hi> of Saint <hi>John</hi> whereon you ground the lawfulneſs of private perſons running into arms and all your ſmiting reſolutions be not directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Chriſts, and the Apoſtles Doctrine, and Practice, let the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Judge, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.38, 39, 40, 43, 44. <hi>You have heard it hath been ſaid, an eye for an eye, and a tooth for a tooth, but I ſay to you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt not evil, but whoſoever ſhall ſmite thee on the right cheek turn the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to him, you have heard that it hath been ſaid, thou ſhalt love thy neighbour and hate thine enemy; but I ſay unto you, love your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115977:3"/>bleſs them that curſe you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them that deſpitfully uſe you and perſecute you,</hi> and by this doctrine he taught nothing but what he lived to. <hi>He was oppreſſed, and he was afflicted,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, Iſa. 53.7, 9. <hi>yet he opened not his mouth, he is brought as a Lamb to the Slaughter, and as a ſheep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Shearers is dumb, ſo he openeth not his mouth,</hi> 50 <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. <hi>I gave my back to the ſmiters, &amp; my checks to them that pluckt off the hair, I hid not my face from ſhame and ſpitting.</hi> When <hi>Peter</hi> conceived with ſmiting thoughts, <hi>John.</hi> 19.11. Chriſt ſaith to him, <hi>Peter put up thy Sword.</hi> When Tribute was demanded of him, by a Heathen King, though he could have pleaded excuſe, choſe rather to work, a Miracle to pay it, and mark, <hi>Leſt I ſhould offend, Matt.</hi> 17. from 24. to 27. When <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>John</hi> would have revenged the unkindneſs of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> to Chriſt, by calling for fire from Heaven to deſtroy them, <hi>He rebuked them,</hi> ſaying, <hi>you know not what Spirit you are of, Luke</hi> 9.55. <hi>For the Son of man came not to deſtroy mens lives, but to ſave them.</hi> Thus we ſee how far Chriſts Spirit, Doctrine, and Practice differeth from yours. Now let us harken to Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 12.18. <hi>If it be poſſible, and as much as in you lyeth, live peaceably with all men. Bleſs them that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute you, bleſs, and curſe not. Let us follow after things that make for peace. Put them in mind to be ſubject to principalities and powers, to obey Magiſtrates, TO SPEAK E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IL OF NO MAN,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.19. 3 <hi>Tit.</hi> 1, 2</note> TO BE NO BRAWLERS but gentle SHEWING ALL MEEKNES TO ALL MEN.</hi> Yea more then all this, he exhorteth, that Prayers, Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions and giving of Thanks, he made not only for Kings, but for <hi>ALL that are in authority,</hi> yea for ſuch that they might have cauſe to fear, would hinder them in godly living, and diſturbe their Chriſtian peace. Why elſe muſt that be the ſubject of their Prayer, that they may live peaceably and quietly under them? and doth he not ſay, that thus to do, is <hi>both good and acceptable in the ſight of God</hi> our <hi>Saviour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt did not intend to become an Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to all private Chriſtians both in Spirit and Practice, in all things of a Morral nature? Such as Gentleneſs, Meekneſs, Love, Humility, and the like; (though not in ſuch things which he did, as God, King, Prieſt, and Prophet, of the Church) that he did intend his own Spirit, and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, in ſuch things to be Exemplary is plain, by <hi>Luke</hi> 9.55. he cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth the intemperate Spirit of his Diſciples by ſhewing them his own. <hi>You know not what Spirit you are of, for the Son of man came not,</hi> &amp;c. The extraordinary practiſes of the Old Teſtament Prophets, was no Pattern to them, but His. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>He that is joyned to the Lord</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115977:4"/>is ſaid to be <hi>one Spirit.</hi> And 2. Phil. 6. <hi>Let the ſame mind be in you which was in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Chriſt calleth upon all his diſciples to learn of him, to be <hi>meek and lowly,</hi> Mat. 11.29. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth upon all Chriſtians, to <hi>walk in love as he did,</hi> 5. Epheſ. 2. to <hi>ſelf-denial,</hi> as he did, 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. <hi>Let every one of you pleaſe his neighbour for his good,</hi> for, <hi>even Chriſt pleaſed not himſelf. Peter</hi> calleth upon all perſons, to Bear Wrongs patiently, as he did, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. and ſo to tread in his ſteps, which, he ſaith, they were thereunto called, from his example. And <hi>John</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.6. <hi>He that ſaith he abideth in him, ought to walk even as he walked.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>We are predeſtinated to be conformed to the Image of the Son,</hi> 8. Rom. 29. And it was his Glory, that looking into the Glaſſe of the Goſpel, he became tranſlated into that Image, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. So then <hi>Chriſts Image, Chriſts Mind, Chriſts Spirit, Chriſts Steps,</hi> is of right the Image of all his Saints, the Mind of all his Diſciples, the Spirit of all his Friends, and the Steps of all his faithfull Followers. Is it not then above an ordinary won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that you ſhould pretend to ſo much of his Spirit, even at the ſame time, when your violent motions proclaim the contrary with a loud voice? Chriſt was all Smooth, and you ſeem to be all Rough. Chriſt was all for putting up of Swords, you are all for pulling them out. Chriſt was all for Saving mens Lives, and you ſeem to be all for Deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them. Chriſt was for Binding up of Wounds, and you are for Making them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether the Commandments and imitable Practiſes of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, before mentioned, be not as long liv'd, as other of his Commandments, and binding upon all his diſciples, till he come again in Perſon. As the People of God under <hi>Moſes,</hi> was ſhut up, as <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſeth it, 3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 23. under his Laws, till Faith, or the Goſpel of the Meſiah come; So are the People of God, under the Goſpel, ſhut up under Chriſts Laws, till He come again in Perſon to diſanull them. onſult, 2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 25. <hi>That which thou haſt received hold faſt:</hi> How long? <hi>TILL I COME.</hi> 1 Cor. 11.26. <hi>As ought as ye eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, ye do ſhew forth the Lords death,</hi> Marke, <hi>TILL HE COME.</hi> So 1 Tim. 6.14. <hi>I give thee charge that thou keep this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment without ſpot, unrebukable.</hi> How long? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NTIL THE APPEARING OF O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST.</hi> So that all the Poſitive Precepts and Examples of Chriſt and the Apoſtles, Practiſed and Commanded upon a Moral Reaſon, laſt as long as this preſent world laſteth, except we ſhould interpret theſe Scriptures, or rather abuſe them with the Quakers, and from them fancy another appearing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115977:4"/>and Coming of Chriſt before his coming to Judgement, but to ſhew the vanity of their conceit. His coming to Judgement is called his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond coming, 9. <hi>Heb.</hi> 28. Whereas then it would be the Third. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider I pray, Is there any Time ſet by our Saviour or the Apoſtles, how long men ſhall be of his Spirit? Humble, Meek, Gentle, <hi>Obedient to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, no brawlers,</hi> but <hi>ſhewing all meekneſſe to all men.</hi> And when his Diſciples may lawfully turn into the quite contrary Spirit, from Lambs to Lyons, from ſubjection to Magiſtrates, to deſtroying them? Tis true there cometh a Time when the Saints ſhall Judge the World, Bind Kings in chains, Rule over Nations, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26. but it is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Overcoming all Temptations, and keeping Chriſts works to the end, even Till He Come. At which time Chriſt promiſeth alſo, to give ſuch Overcomers <hi>the Morning Star,</hi> 2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 28. Look the place. Now as you go to work, you catch at the Reward before you have done your Work. The Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> enjoyneth upon all the Chriſtians, patience, <hi>James</hi> 5.7, 8, 9. <hi>Be patient therefore Brethren,</hi> ſaith he, How long? <hi>unto the coming of the Lord.</hi> The mean Time is the Time of Saints ſuffering not Raigning, in the Judgement of S. <hi>James,</hi> And is not <hi>Paul</hi> one with him, Marke 3. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 4. <hi>WHEN CHRIT WHO IS O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R LIFE ſhall appear THEN ſhall ye appear with him in glory.</hi> Mark that <hi>THEN,</hi> and not till then, for he ſaith, in the mean Time, <hi>they are dead, and their life is hid.</hi> Now, How are they dead, and their Life hid, if they muſt pull down Princes, and be the Earths Governours?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether doth not <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet tell us plainly in the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Daniel</hi> 21. <hi>That the Horn that ſpake great things, and whoſe looks were more ſtout then his fellows, that this horn ſhould make warre with the Saints, and prevail againſt them untill the Ancient of Days come:</hi> If ſo, and that it appears by the 13. <hi>Verſe</hi> as it plainly doth, That the Time of the Ancient of Daies coming, and the Son of Mans coming in the clouds of Heaven take place together. Mind the words <hi>Behold one like the Son of man came with the clouds of heaven, and came to the Ancient of daies, and they brought him near.</hi> If ſo, then how vain a thing is it to expect the Kingdomes of this world to become Chriſts till he come in the clouds of Heaven, and the Ancient of dayes with him?</p>
            <p n="8">8. Some of you make <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.18. (The words theſe, <hi>But the Saints ſhall take the Kingdome</hi>) the ground of preſent fighting with world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Powers in order thereunto, now the Query is, Whether this be not a wild inference from the Premiſes, becauſe tis clear from the 27. <hi>Verſe</hi> that when ever they take it, <hi>it ſhall be firſt given them,</hi> and that's not till
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115977:5"/>the Ancient of days come: So ſaith the 22. <hi>Verſe, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill the Ancient of daies come, and Judgement was given to the Saints of the moſt High, and the time came that the Saints poſſeſſed the Kingdom.</hi> Nay Chriſt himſelf hath it not actually given him, till his coming in the clouds of Heaven, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. Marke the words, <hi>Behold one like the Son of man came with the clouds of heaven, and came to the Ancient of daies, and they brought him near before him, and there was GI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EN HIM Glory, Dominion, and a Kingdom.</hi> Can any one with any ſhew of reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that God would have the Saints to take the Kingdom before it be given Chriſt, Is not this then a ſtrang piece of Religion in the People of God: Now in the dayes of their conformity to Chriſt in his humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to leave the Rode of all Gods Saints to leap over the Hedge of all poſitive Laws, and break down the Wall of moſt plain Precepts, to pull down Kings and Princes in order thereunto?</p>
            <p n="9">9. Doth not the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> inſtruct us, that the Time of Chriſts Reign over the Kingdoms of this world, taketh place with the ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the laſt Trumpet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. Mind the words, And the <hi>Seventh Angel ſounded and there were great voyces, in heaven ſaying, The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of this world are become the Kingdomes of our Lord, and of his Chriſt.</hi> And the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.52. ſaith thus, <hi>In a Moment in the Twinkling of an eye at the laſt Trumpet, for the Trumpet ſhall ſound and the dead ſhall be raiſed.</hi> So then, if the Time of Chriſts Reign over the Kingdomes of this world take place, with the ſounding of the laſt Trumpet, which is <hi>Johns</hi> Doctrine; And the ſounding of the laſt Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet be at the Time of the Reſurrection of the Dead, which is <hi>Pauls</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; Then how vain a thing is it to expect the Fifth Monarchy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt till after the firſt Reſurrection?</p>
            <p n="10">10. Whether by the Stone cut out of the Mountaine without hands be not meant <hi>Chriſt</hi> with the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> onely, or at leaſt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally? Becauſe the ſame Work that <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith the Stone ſhall do, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.3.4.35. The ſame Work the men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall do: See alſo and compare the 41. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14, 15, 16. Who 12. <hi>Zach.</hi> 3. are called, <hi>a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome ſtone.</hi> And is it not harſh dealing in the Interpretation of Scripture, to put that upon the <hi>Gentile</hi> Saints, which the Scripture fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on the men of <hi>Jſrael,</hi> where do we find the <hi>Gentiles</hi> called <hi>the men of Iſrael,</hi> in all the Word of God?</p>
            <p n="11">11. Whether the deſtruction of the Whore of <hi>Rome,</hi> is not plainly declared to be the work of the Ten Hornes, and not the Saints as Saints, Though the Saints in common with the World may be uſed in the Work, as they are Members of thoſe Common-Wealths, over whom thoſe Horns have Power, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.16. <hi>The ten horns which thou SAWEST,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115977:5"/>Theſe ſhall hate the Whore, and make her deſolate and naked, and ſhall eat her fleſh, and burn it with fire.</hi> For the Saints as Saints to go about it then, is to croſs the word of God, and I fear to run before they are ſent.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Whether you are not in a great Errour, when you ſay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Banner of Truth,</hi> p 19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that the Stone ſpoken of <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. you find it to be Chriſt Jeſus in the pure ſanctified and refined <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians. To prove this, you urge in the firſt place, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.2, 3. The words are as followeth, <hi>But who may abide the day of his coming, and who ſhall ſtand when he appeareth? For he is like refiners fire and fullers ſope, and he ſhall ſit as a refiner and purifier of ſilver. And he ſhall purify the Sons of Levi, and purge them as gold and ſilver, then ſhall the offering of Jndah and Jeruſalem be pleaſant unto the Lord, as in the dayes of Old.</hi> But how you ſhould conclude the Text ſpeaking of the <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians is ſtrange. Are the <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians called by the Name of the Sons of <hi>Levi?</hi> The Perſons of the Text are Sons of <hi>Levi,</hi> Sons of <hi>Jacob, v.</hi> 6. ſuch as then were under the Law of Tithes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. and are ſaid to rob God in not paying of them, Therefore not <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Text you urge to prove, the Stone in <hi>Daniel</hi> is meant of Chriſt in the <hi>Gentile</hi> Saints, picked not out of the World onely, but Churches alſo is the 14. <hi>Revel.</hi> 4, 5. but very impertinently in my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion; Becauſe the picked holy perſons there ſpoken of, are ſaid to be, <hi>One hundred fourty and four thouſand,</hi> which if we will ſuffer <hi>John</hi> to tell us who they are, we muſt needs underſtand them, of the Sealed <hi>Jews,</hi> of the Twelve Tribes of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.4. and not the <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians. Mind the Words, <hi>And I heard the number of them that were ſealed, and there were ſealed One hundred fourty and four thouſand:</hi> Now mark who they were, <hi>OF ALL THE TRIBES OF THE CHILDREN OF ISRAEL;</hi> and ſo goeth on to the 8. <hi>verſe,</hi> to mention thoſe Tribes particularly; Therefore not the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Thirdly, to prove that the ſtone, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. that ſhall break in pieces and conſume the Kingdomes of the Earth, is not to be meant of Chriſt with the <hi>Jews,</hi> but of Chriſt in the <hi>Gentile</hi> Saints, you urge Chriſts words in the 21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 42. where he is ſpoken of under the Metaphor of a ſtone. And where Chriſt telleth the <hi>Jews,</hi> that the <hi>Kingdom of God ſhould be taken from them &amp; given to a nation bringing forth the fruits thereof.</hi> From hence you conclude, that the ſmiting work of the Kingdomes of the world will be done by the <hi>Gentiles</hi> firſt, and not the <hi>Jewes.</hi> Here your Error lieth in the miſtake of the ſence of thoſe words, <hi>The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115977:6"/>of God,</hi> ſpoken of is the 21. <hi>Math.</hi> In that place it noteth onely the Goſpel of the Kingdome, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.13. which <hi>Luke</hi> 10.9. Chriſt ſaid, was come nigh to them; And 17. <hi>Luke</hi> 21. Chriſt ſaid, was amongſt them: And in this ſenſe, the Kingdome of God was taken from them, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46. according to Chriſts threat: But you uſe the words, to note the Kingdome of his viſible Power and Dominion, as a viſible King over the <hi>Jewes,</hi> which they were not in poſſeſſion of: Therefore not capable of a Threat to have it removed. Yea though Chriſt had the Right of all Power given to him by the Father, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. yet not the right of actual exerciſe of all that Power at the ſame time: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.8.9.</note> when <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> had ſaid, <hi>He hath put all things under his feet,</hi> preſently ſubjoyneth, <hi>But we ſee not YET all things put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his feet.</hi> Yea Chriſt telleth his Diſciples, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.7. That the Time of Reſtoring the Kingdome to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was not for them to know. And finding ſome of his Diſciples, ſuppoſing his Kingdome, in your ſenſe would immediately appear, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.11. He putteth a Parable on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to rectify them, the Subſtance whereof is, that he muſt go to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and receive Orders for it, and return again before he execute it: Which directly anſwereth to 7. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 15. and 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. where his Kingdom and appearing are put as taking place together.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Whether, when Chriſt ſaith, <hi>My Kingdome is not of this world,</hi> or, <hi>from hence,</hi> as he expoundeth himſelf, <hi>John</hi> 18.36. giving this for the Reaſon why, his ſervants fight not for him: Doth not this Text reprove with a high hand, all humane force to enthrone him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently condemn your practiſe, becauſe he ſaith. <hi>My Kingdome is not from hence,</hi> that is from the World, or worldly Powers, as the Kingdomes of other Monarchs were,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.31. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.25. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.16.</note> but from above; from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Things of and from the world, from men, and from the earth, are oppoſed in other Scriptures, to being from above, from heaven, from the Father? Here then ſeemeth to be Chriſts Argument, if he were to come by his Kingdome, as other Kings ordinarily come by theirs, His ſervants would Fight for him, as the ſervants of other Monarchs fight for them, but ſince he was to come by his, from another Power then that of men, his ſervants need not be buſie with Armes for him, as other Kings are for them.</p>
            <p>But it ſeemeth, ſome of you are of opinion, that the word <hi>NOW,</hi> is Emphaticall, in that 18. of <hi>John</hi> 36. where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>But Now my Kingdom is not from hence,</hi> implying, there would come a Time when it would be from the World, and that before his perſonall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing. To that I anſwer, Firſt, The word <hi>NOW</hi> is ordinarily
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115977:6"/>uſed in Scripture, without any Emphaſis at all; as 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. And there is this reaſon why it ſhould be ſo underſtood here. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to underſtand it to point at the Time preſent onely, that Chriſts Kingdome was not then, at that Time of the World, and to make it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply there would be a Time before his coming, wherein it ſhould. I ſay, thus to underſtand it, would make more Diviſions of the World, then the Scripture owneth. We read of three, and but three. The firſt from the Creation to the Flood, called <hi>the Old World,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. Secondly, from the Flood to Chriſts Second coming,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> called <hi>THIS WORLD:</hi> And Thirdly, from Chriſts Second appearing to the end of his Raign, called 2 <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. <hi>The World to come.</hi> Now your Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the word <hi>NOW,</hi> maketh a Fourth, Namely, one between the time of Chriſts ſpeaking thoſe Words, and his Second coming, which is not found in Scripture. But again, Secondly, I anſwer, Though it were admitted that the word <hi>Now,</hi> ſhould be Imphatical, and ſignifie a time wherein Chriſt Kingdome would be of the World, or from the world, yet it croſſeth your doctrine; becauſe you ſay, the Saints as Saints muſt fight for him, to enthrone him, you know the Saints are contra-diſtinguiſhed from the world, and ſaid to be choſen out of it, <hi>John</hi> 15.19. So that which way ſoever you turn this text, it fighteth againſt you, not for you. Thirdly, if there had been any time between that expreſſion of his and, his Second coming wherein he would have his Servants turn deſtroyers of men inſtead of Saviours, and walk ſo contrary to himſelf and the plain Laws he had given in <hi>Matt.</hi> 5 to all his followers; ſurely he would have been very plain in telling us when that time ſhould begin, and when a period ſhould be put to thoſe poſitive Laws given in that moſt excellent Sermon on the Mount</p>
            <p n="15">15. Whether you are not commanded in the, 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 17. To provide things honeſt in the fight of all men, and was not this <hi>Pauls</hi> care, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.21. <hi>Providing for honeſt things not only in the ſight of God, but in the ſight of men,</hi> And is not that a Scripture exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be obayed by all Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.33. <hi>give no offence neither to the Jew, nor to the Gentile, nor to the Church of God,</hi> and if ſo; Whether it is poſſible to give a greater offence both to the one and to the other; and do any thing more diſhoneſt in the ſight of every man, then for private perſons under the notion and name of Saints, that can work no more Miracles then other men, to countenance what they pretend to,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. 11. <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 16.</note> whoſe profeſſion is to be <hi>ſtrangers and Pilgrims on earth,</hi> to expect a <hi>building of God, a houſe not made with hands, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in the Heavens,</hi> after the example of <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115977:7"/>faithful,
<note place="margin">12 <hi>Rom.</hi> 17.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 19. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>not to mind high things nor to avenge themſelves, not to ſtrive but to be gentle towards all men, meek and lowly, having food and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therewith to be content;</hi> Now for ſuch to turn head upon all the great principles of Chriſtian Religion, according to the Judgment of all men upon the Scriptures, to grow impatient, heady, high-minded, to do that to others which they would not that others ſhould do to them; and without any reſpect to the poſitive Law of God, and natural rights of men, to force the Thrones of Kings and worldly Powers, and to give Laws to the Nations; Saying under Chriſt we muſt raign; I ſay, Whether is it poſſible for men to be more ſcandelous, and do things more diſhoneſt in the ſight of every man?</p>
            <p n="16">16. Whether is there not a great appearance of evil in your pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fight, that Chriſt may raign, whereas Chriſt doth not perſonally appear to raign, and utterly diſclaimeth as you have heard his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to be of this world, ſome of your ſelves doubt whether ever he will viſibly appear on earth at all or no, what then will the thoughts of men be of you, if ever you ſhould run upon any boyſterous engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that through ſome bitter root or other, you would pull down thoſe in power to advance your ſelves and for a cloak, talk of Chriſt &amp; his raign or at beſt that you are ſpiritually intoxicated through ſome enthuſiaſtical fancy, this muſt needs be the thoughts of the moſt except you could ſhew a Commiſſion from Chriſt, to take the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of this world under his hand and ſeal, that all men may know you deputed by Chriſt thereto from all others <hi>that make no ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. Whether your judgment, being that the perſons uſed in this ſmiting work ſhall be of an extraordinary qualification for goodneſs, pure, ſanctified, refined, purged as gold and ſilver, as the text you urge from <hi>Malachy</hi> ſpeaketh, And as <hi>John;</hi> undefiled <hi>Virgins, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from amongſt men, from the earth, And in whoſe mouth is found no guile, and ſo without fault before the Throne of God;</hi> I ſay, do not you by this deſcription of the men that ſhal be uſed in this work either bewray the intemperate opinion you have, of your own good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and worth, or elſe publiſh to the world with a loud voyce, that you are not the men, for the preſent fitted for the work; is there any one man amongſt you; or indeed in the whole world, able to ſay I am pure refined, purged as gold, undefiled, redeemed for the earth, I am without fault before the Throne of God, if you ſay you cannot ſay ſo, why then do you entertain one thought, to engage in ſuch high and mighty work, which is proper only to ſuch by your own confeſſion.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115977:7"/>
            <p n="18">18 Whether height of confidence, boldneſs to ſuffer, ſence of comfort, be any Argument alone of being in the Truth, <hi>Paul</hi> was high in confidence, that he pleaſed God, when he draged the Saints to priſon, <hi>Acts</hi> 26. <hi>I verily thought, I ought to do many things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Name of Jeſus.</hi> Doth not Chriſt ſay, <hi>they ſhall kill you</hi> and think <hi>they do God good ſervice?</hi> 9. <hi>John</hi> 40. The Phariſees,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.2.</note> 
               <hi>Are we alſo blind?</hi> And yet who ſo blind? Are any more bold to ſuffer, more confident of being in the Truth then the poor deluded <hi>Quakers?</hi> If theſe things alone be no ſolid Argument of being in the the Truth, then be intreated to found your notions &amp; practiſes upon the never erring Word of God, rationally interpreted, or let them go, 8. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 20. <hi>To the Law and to the teſtimony, if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi> 6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 16. <hi>As many as walk according to THIS R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LE peace be on them,</hi> who ever ſindeth peace in a way contrary to Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Rule, may be ſure tis not the Peace of God, <hi>Phil</hi> 4.7. but the peace of Satan, which he is wont to give poor creatures that he hath in faſt poſſeſſion, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.21.</p>
            <p n="19">19. <note place="margin">John Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caldus <hi>Redivium.</hi> Or the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Quaker</hi> you may read at large.</note> Whether that Spirit that worketh mightily in you in theſe ſmighting reſolutions, be not the ſame that wrought in <hi>Munſter,</hi> and others, that at laſt iſſued in all manner of ungodlineſſe, and confuſion, which I believe is farre from your hearts to deſign.</p>
            <p>Do you complain of Princes Tyranny, and Luxury to the People? So did they.</p>
            <p>Do you cry up the Kingdome of Chriſt on Earth, and pretend for Righteouſneſſe? So did they.</p>
            <p>Do you cry up your ſelves for the little remnant, the refined People that are appointed to ſmiting work? So did they.</p>
            <p>Do you revile the reputed Orthodox Miniſtery for Antichriſtian, Carnall? So did they.</p>
            <p>Do you open the Pulpit to common men of all Trades? So did they.</p>
            <p>Do you go much by inward impulſes? So did they.</p>
            <p>Do you uſe the Scripture Inſtances of <hi>Jonathan</hi> &amp; his Armour-Bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Gideon</hi> againſt the <hi>Midianites,</hi> &amp; <hi>David</hi> againſt <hi>Goliah,</hi> to heighten the Peoples Spirits to fight. So did <hi>Munſters,</hi> in his Oration before the fight with the Princes, uſe the ſame?</p>
            <p>Do you abound with comfort, peace, confidence of ſucceſſe, ſo did they? <hi>Munſter</hi> to encourage the People to fight, told them he was ſure of Victory. Now then conſider in the fear of God, whether this ſimilitude doth not evince, that <hi>they then,</hi> and <hi>you now,</hi> are acted much by oneand the ſelf-ſame Spirit, and if ſo, Whether you have not cauſe to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115977:8"/>judge that you have gotten the wrong Spirit for your guide, and your foot in a moſt dangerous ſnare, (notwithſtanding all your confidence to the contrary) ſince not only Gods Word, but Gods fearful Judgements upon the Ringleaders of the <hi>German</hi> Rebellion, did, &amp; do with a loud voice declare his diſlike of their actions, there not being one Head-manamongſt them, according to the Story, but proved forſaken of the good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, and ſtruck with Blindneſſe of Mind, and Hardneſſe of Heart. And whether you have not juſt cauſe to fear the like fearfull judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God to befall you, if you ſhould perſiſt in obedience to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of that evil Spirit, that now prompteth you to leap out of your Places and Callings, to meddle with Perſons and Things you have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with: Since <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>God of order and not of confuſion;</hi> And <hi>the Father that without reſpect of perſons judgeth every mans work</hi> 1 Pet. 1.17.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Whether your Contempt of the godly learned Miniſtry of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be not evidently of the <hi>evil Spirit?</hi> ſince all the great ends for which Chriſt ordained a Goſpel Miniſtry, is not onely endeavoured but actually effected, by many of them, and conſequently the Marks and Characters of the Miniſters of Chriſt are upon them, ſince it is impoſſible ſuch work ſhould be done, but by the concurrence of Gods holy Spirit with them. For <hi>though Paul plant and Apollo water,</hi> Tis <hi>God muſt give the increaſe.</hi> If you could ſhew half ſo much for your Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning the World, as they can for their Miniſtry, you might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter expect Subjection by the Inhabitants of the Earth. There are Four things chiefly to which the work of the Miniſters of Chriſt, by divine appointment, may be reduced. Firſt, Conviction of Sin &amp; Righteouſnſs, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.8.18. <hi>Act.</hi> 28. Secondly, Converſion, 26. <hi>Acts</hi> 18. Thirdly, Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. 4. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 12. Fourthly, Protection, 20. <hi>Acts,</hi> 28, 29. None of which can be denied to be wrought by many of them. The truth of which is manifeſt. 1. By the multitude of bils of ſpiritual complaints, requeſts and thanks givings made evident daily by ſuch as wait on the Publick miniſtry. 2. Particular addreſſes of perſons to their houſes, to be reſolved in caſes of conſcience upon their Miniſtry. 3. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, early, chearfull attendance of multitudes of Chriſtians, upon their Miniſtry daily, to receive their Fathers bread by their hand. 4. The holy Converſation of many that are fed by them. 5. The freedome of ſuch from the grand Hereſies of the Time wherewith divers others are infected, Hereticks having little to do with any but ſuch as have firſt fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len in their affection to them, and at laſt turned their backs upon them. 6. The tears &amp; ſad hearts of many godly ſouls at the death of them, as late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115977:8"/>at the death of Mr. <hi>Jacombe.</hi> Now then, if they do all the work of the Miuiſters of Chriſt, and all the ends for which Chriſt ordained the Miniſtry be accompliſhed by them, which could not be done without God, why then God owneth them, Chriſt owneth them, and the Spirit of God owneth them; Whence then can it be but from the evil Spirit that you diſown them, and pour contempt upon them?</p>
            <p>Now the Lord give you to conſider this, and in the ſpirit of love &amp; meekneſs I ſpeak to you, remembring what poor weak creatures we are all, and that I my ſelf have been in the like kind tempted, &amp; to ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree overcome, for which I abhor my ſelf in duſt and aſhes. I further intreat you to conſider if God peradventure will give you repentance to the acknowledging of the truth, that as in the contempt of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learned Miniſtry, you fall <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T</hi> of the company of God, <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T</hi> of the company of Chriſt, <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T</hi> of the company of the Spirit, as hath been ſhewn, <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T</hi> of the company of the bleſſed Martyrs and glorified Saints who greatly reverenſed the godly Miniſtry of their time, <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T</hi> of the company of almoſt all the people of God, upon the face of the whole earth at the preſent time, ſo on the other hand, I intreat you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider whoſe company you fall <hi>INTO</hi> even all ſorts of perſons enmpt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the good, and full of the evil ſpirit, comrades of Satan; who are like to be throne into the lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone for ever, theſe all as one man, hate the godly Miniſtry, and moſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently ſet themſelves againſt them, yea, 'tis remarkable, that the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men are from God the greater is their hatred of them, and can you find in your heart to be found in ſuch company.</p>
            <p n="1">1. All ſorts of prophane wretches, in whoſe Souls the good ſpirits never lodged, ſuch as reſiſt the holy Ghoſt, and will not that Chriſt ſhould raign over them, theſe all hate a puritan Miniſter, becauſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Propheſie to them of Wine or ſtrong drink, or any thing that will pleaſe them; Secondly, all Apoſtates from the faith of Gods elect, out of whoſe ſouls the good ſpirit is <hi>departed,</hi> as the <hi>Ranters</hi> and <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> that have let go the <hi>head,</hi> there are no perſons ſo venemouſly ſet againſt them as theſe: as appeareth by their Pamphlets and <hi>WHY</hi> but becauſe thoſe greevous Wolves cannot devour the Lambs of Chriſt; ſo freely as they would, while the poor people, have the wings of godly and learned men to ſhelter them? Thirdly the Pope with his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> theſe ſtrive all they can to hinder the ſucceſs of their Miniſtry, and indeed to ruin both them and their ſtanding, inſinuate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the people, that they are no Miniſters, only lay-men; Their ſtanding in the Miniſtry naught, becauſe they have not their Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115977:9"/>from Rome, while you on the other hand ſay their ſtanding is naught, becauſe <hi>they have</hi> their Ordination from Rome. But beſides all this, <hi>HE</hi> by all baſe means reproacheth them, as carnal, vitions, and if he can light of them he burneth them, and why doth be all this? Is it becauſe their Miniſterial ſtanding is Antichriſtian think ye, as you ſuggeſt, or the quite contrary, the Pope and you are of two minds in this, were the Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> bone of his bone and fleſh of his fleſh as you are apt to think, he would noriſh and cheriſh them, not bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ruin and deſtroy them, no man ever hated his own fleſh, but nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cheriſhed it, the truth is, his hatred to them is founded upon his knowledg of the quite contrary: Namely, that if he cannot procure them to fall off their ſtanding (wherein you work hard to help him though not intentionally) he is never like to get up his in <hi>England,</hi> he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth well enough that as they ever have been, ſo ſtill are, under God, the Walls, and Bullworks of the Proteſtant Religion, and that beſides them he hath no conſiderable adverſary hear; there not being many beſides able to read one line; nay not one word of the Bible, but by their help, now then if they have God, Chriſt, Spirit, with them, and the generality of the godly, over the face of the whole earth with them: and againſt them, all ſorts of ungodly wretches as in a conſpiracy, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks it ſhould rationally put you to a ſtand and make you tremble when you or any other go about to ſpeak evil of ſuch dignities: Again is it <hi>Satan</hi> in them? that's certain; becauſe they have no other guide, and becauſe he ſeeketh the deſtruction of Souls, and can it be God in you to deſtroy the Saviours of Souls. You cannot ſwear with them, norly with them, nor be drunk with them, nor commit uncleaneſs with them, nor blaſpheme God, nor commit Idolatry with them: how cometh it that you can revile the Godly learned Miniſtry with them? For the Lords ſake, the Goſpel ſake, the poor divided Church &amp; people of Gods ſake, and for your own eternal Savlation ſake, conſider what you do in this great matter, leſt you be found fighters againſt God, whilſt you think to fight for him, and fighters for the Pope whilſt you think to fight againſt him.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Bleſſed are the Pace-makers, for they ſhall be called the Children of God:
<bibl>
                     <hi>Matt. 5.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
